A Guide to the Old Dominion Humanities Institute, Office Administrative Files, 1951-1972
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Old Dominion Humanities Institute, Office Administrative Files 1951-1972
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-10/6/1.791
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was an archival transfer in 1979.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Old Dominion Humanities Institute was a summer program for teachers, held at the University of Virginia during the summers of 1966-1971. The primary objectives of the Institute were to integrate humanities disciplines and to introduce high school teachers to new approaches to the humanities. The Institute spawned the Humanities Development Panel to provide follow-up assistance for Institute fellows as they developed and altered approaches to teaching as a result of their attendance at the Institute. General information on the Institute can be found in the "Reference Files" in Box 1.
Scope and Content
The records include correspondence, publicity, budgets, lists and schedules, minutes, notes and teaching files, evaluations of the Institute, and student work for the years 1951-1972.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in three series: Series I, Reference Files, 1951-1969; Series II, Records of Annual Sessions, 1966-1972; and, Series III, Applicants' files, 1966-1971.
Contents List
- Series I: Reference Files
  - Humanities Courses, 11 folders, 1951-1969 (Folder 1)
  - Articles, Reports, and Notes, ca. 1966 (Folder 1)
  - Printed Material, ca. 1966 (Folder 1)
- Series II: Records of Annual Sessions
  - Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Folder 2)
  - Publicity, Budget, Schedules, 1966 (Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1966 (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2 folders, 1967 (Folder 2)
  - Publicity, Budget, Schedules, 1967 (Folder 2)
  - Participants, 1967 (Folder 2)
  - Panel Members Questions, 1967 (Folder 2)
  - Minutes and Reports, 1967 (Folder 2)
  - Book Lists and Curricula, 1967 (Folder 2)
  - Poems, 1967 (Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Papers, 1967 (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2 folders, 1968 (Folder 2)
  - Conversation: Gianniny and Frescolm, 1968 (Folder 3)
  - Publicity, 1968 (Folder 3)
  - Budget and Financial Papers, 1967-1968 (Folder 3)
  - Participants, Schedules, 1968 (Folder 3)
  - Minutes and Notes on Meetings, 1967-1968 (Folder 3)
  - Opening Statement by Jerri Sutton, 1968 (Folder 3)
  - Book Lists, 1967-1968 (Folder 3)
  - Teaching Materials: Background, 1955 (Folder 3)
  - Humanities Development Project Field Service Plan, 1968 (Folder 3)
  - "Aids for Planning Programs...a loose leaf packet", 1968 (Folder 3)
  - Questionnaires, 1968 (Folder 3)
  - Literature Lecture Notes, 1968 (Folder 3)
  - Poems, 1968 (Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Papers, 1968 (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 3 folders, 1969 (Folder 4)
  - Letters to Principals, 1969 (Folder 4)
  - Publicity, 1969 (Folder 4)
  - Budget, 1969 (Folder 4)
  - Participants, Schedules, 1969 (Folder 4)
  - Minutes and Notes on Meetings, 1969 (Folder 4)
  - Virginia Education Association Conference, 1969 (Folder 4)
  - Opening Address by Mrs. Jean Dyson, 1969 (Folder 4)
  - Questionnaires, 1969 (Folder 4)
  - Working Notes, 1969 (Folder 4)
  - Poetry 1969 (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence- 3 folders, 1970 (Folder 5)
  - Publicity, 1970 (Folder 5)
  - Budget and Financial Papers, 1970 (Folder 5)
  - Schedules, 1970 (Folder 5)
  - Participants, 1970 (Folder 5)
  - Advisory Committee Meetings, 1970 (Folder 5)
  - Humanities Development Panel Meetings, 1970 (Folder 5)
  - Fifth National Conference on the Humanities, 1970 (Folder 5)
  - Virginia Commission on the Arts and Humanities Camp, 1970 (Folder 1970)
  - Petersburg Education Association, 1969-1970 (Folder 5)
  - Dilenowsico Project, 1970 (Folder 5)
  - Wise County Conference, 1970 (Folder 1970)
  - Humanities Development Panel Curriculum Group, 1970 (Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and Papers re ASCO Commission on the Humanities, 1970-1972 (Folder 6)
  - Opening Address by Vera Rathkamp, 1970 (Folder 6)
  - Newsletter, Humanities Devlopment Panel, 1970 (Folder 6)
  - Material re Evaluation of Institute and NEH Proposal, 1970 (Folder 6)
  - Questionnaires, 2 folders, 1970 (Folder 6)
  - Working Notes, 1970 (Folder 6)
  - Drug Education, A Project, 1972 (Folder 6)
  - 1970 (Box-folder 6)
  - Play Plots, 1970 (Folder 6)
  - Poems, 1970 (Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 2 folders, 1971 (Folder 7)
  - Publicity and Application Material, 1971 (Folder 7)
  - Budget and Financial Papers, 1971 (Folder 7)
  - Participants, Schedules, Booklist, 1971 (Folder 7)
  - Minutes and Notes on Meetings and Conferences, 1971 (Folder 7)
  - Annual Teachers Conference, Roanoke, 1971 (Folder 7)
  - Questionnaires and Evaluations, 1971 (Folder 7)
  - Material re NEH Proposal, 1971 (Folder 7)
  - Newsletter and Reports, 1971 (Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1971 (Folder 7)
  - Poetry, 1971 (Folder 7)
  - Photographs, ca. 1966-1971 (Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Folder 7)
  - Budget and Financial Papers, 1972 (Folder 7)
  - Newsletters, 1972 (Folder 7)
  - Meeting on Governor's School, 1972 October (Folder 7)
  - Team- Building Workshop, 1972 (Folder 7)
- Series III: Applicant's Files
  - HDP Biographical Statement, 1966-1971 (Folder 8)
  - A- J, 9 folders, 1966-1971 (Folder 8)
  - K- Z, 7 folders, 1966-1971 (Folder 9)